We are learning sobering new details
about what President Trump initially
knew about the Corona virus and when he
knew it. According to a new book by Bob
Woodward, the president knew of the
dangers of the virus weeks before the
first death in the US. Instead of
warning the American people, the
president decided to play the virus
down. Woodward recorded two separate
conversations he had with the president
for the book. One from February, the
other from March. Here is some of what
the president told him as obtained by
CNN.
It goes through air, Bob. That's always
tougher than the touch. You know, the
touch, you don't have to touch things,
right? But the air, you just breathe the
air and that's how it's uh passed. And
so, that's a very tricky one. That's a
very delicate one. Uh it's also more
deadly than your, you know, your even
your strenuous flu. This is more deadly.
This is five per, you know, this is 5%
versus 1% and less than 1%. You know, so
this is deadly stuff.
Well, I think Bob, really, to be honest
with you,
Sure. I want you to
I wanted to uh I wanted to always play
it down. I still like playing it down.
Yes.
Because I don't want to create a panic.
Let's bring in Jacqueline Alamy now.
She's a political reporter and author of
the PowerUp newsletter for the
Washington Post. Jackie, welcome. Great
to have you with us. So, since this news
broke, you tweeted a video showing 54
times that President Trump downplayed
the Corona virus. How had the White
House been defending that in the past
and how do these tapes impact that?
Well, look, what we see here is a a
pattern that reporters have been drawing
out from the administration's handling
of the Coronairus pandemic um since
February. But what these tapes really
confirm on the record in Trump's own
words is that there is a disparity
between what the president knew in
private, what his his administration
knew in private, and what the president
was conveying to the American public um
throughout his handling of the pandemic.
and throughout his refusal to fully
mobilize the federal government uh in
order to tackle this problem even as he
knew and was getting intel as he told
Bob Woodward um that he was hearing from
people like President Xi uh and getting
information that the virus was very
deadly. On January 28th, um the Post
first reported that that's when Trump's
national security adviser, Robert
O'Brien, warned the president that this
pandemic would be the roughest thing
that he would ever face in his
presidency. Uh Woodward and the
president spoke a week after that,
February 7th, where Trump disclosed this
information and also added that he had
received information from President Xi.
Yet the rest of the month of February,
what Woodward deems a lost month in
terms of handling the Corona virus
pandemic, the president insisted that
the country was at a very low risk, that
the virus would simply disappear and
continued to make comments that really
again downplayed the virus. Um, and as
really you can see in in that video that
the post compiled of the 54 different
times that he downplayed the virus
despite what the White House press
secretary Kaye McManny claimed during
the the White House briefing today. Um,
that the president was simply trying to
uh remain calm and assure the the public
uh that things were going to be okay and
that in fact he wasn't misleading the
public. But Woodward's account uh really
shows that that's just not the case.
And there is a lot coming out from
Woodward's reporting in his new book
beyond just what we're learning about
the president's handling of the
pandemic. Woodward also says that
President Trump revealed the existence
of a secret new nuclear weapons system.
He says this was later confirmed by
anonymous sources who were surprised the
president disclosed it. How significant
is that?
We are still reaching out to our sources
right now to try to gain more
information on this pretty shocking
development ourselves. But I think what
it underscores is what we've known about
this president over the past few years
of his administration. um you know, a
very relaxed um and uh you know, an
approach to the intelligence community
um and intelligent in general, that
concerns a lot of national security
types, including his own adviserss,
current and former, who have expressed
dismay with the way the president
handles classified information, and how
he discloses it very cavalerely to
either authoritarian leaders who he has
deemed his friends, which Woodward also
details. details throughout the book um
or to reporters in conversations that
intelligence officials uh are later
surprised by. Um, but it's pretty
jarring when the administration is
actively trying to shield information
from getting to Democrats on the Hill
um, and preventing, you know, the
transmission of classified information
with regards to Russian interference in
the election, but then is on the phone
with Bob Woodward disclosing uh, pretty
big news that the US has a is has
developed a new nuclear weapon system.
And Jackie Woodward also repeatedly
questioned the president about the
nationwide protests for racial justice
this summer following the police killing
of George Floyd. What did the president
have to say about those?
Yeah, Tanya, that's a really interesting
conversation that Woodward details as
well. You know, as you just noted, there
are 18 different on there interviews
that the two had together that are
taped. Uh Woodward says to Trump that
the two have more in common than they
realize. They're both white and of
privilege. Um and the president uh
responds to Woodward saying that um he's
really drank the Kool-Aid and that he
doesn't see things that way and doesn't
necessarily agree with Woodward's
assessment that as men of white
privilege um that they owe the
African-American community support,
especially from the federal government.
I think that the that claim is not
necessarily surprising but especially
startling coming after the Republican
National Convention where there was a
series of speakers who explicitly said
that the president cared about black
voters that uh he was not racist. All of
these validators who came out to try to
bolster the president's flagging numbers
with African-American voters. I think
what it also really underscores is just
how transactional Trump views his
relationship with voters. He also says
to Woodward that he's shown the black
community a lot of love and he doesn't
get anything back. Um the president is
time has time and time again shown that
he believes um that you know his
position when he does things for certain
communities that in return he is owed
some sort of political reward or
electoral support.
And Jackie Woodward also spoke with
several current and former members of
the Trump administration. How did they
in general describe their interactions
with the president?
That's exactly right. He spoke with
former um DNI director Dan Coats um who
was an Indiana Senator and and pretty
close with the uh Vice President Mike
Pence. Um he also has conversations um
from sources of things that his former
uh defense secretary Jim Mattis told him
saying that the president had no moral
compass. Um he details this pretty grim
scene of Mattis going to the Washington
Cathedral to say a prayer um for the
president and saying that you know his
moral compass was so concerning that he
was praying for the country and and for
the government and and told coats that
they thought that they might have to
take things at some point into their own
hands. All of this, I think, sort of
butresses a lot of the, you know, uh,
reporting that we've seen from the
Atlantic, um, and from all of the media
outlets that confirm the Atlantic,
Atlantic's reporting about the
president's relationship with with the
military, many of his military and
national security advisers who
expressed, you know, a uh, deep concern
for the president and the president's
loathing of them in return. um he goes
uh on the record here and calls is
pretty disparaging of the military um
which his administration just really
spent the last week denying. Uh so I
think that all of these comments really
could put the president in even deeper
of a hole. Um but again, I think it's
really worth noting that the president
has publicly disparaged veterans um
before, but it is uh eye opening when
you have officials now sourced um you
know by name as saying some of these
things.
Jacqueline Alamy, thank you so much for
joining us. We really appreciate it.
Thanks for having